On our arrival in Denmark, we found the king and queen of that country elevated
in two arm-chairs on a kitchen-table, holding a Court. The whole of the Danish nobility were in
attendance; consisting of a noble boy in the wash-leather boots of a gigantic ancestor,
a venerable Peer with a dirty face who seemed to have risen from the people late in life,
and the Danish chivalry with a comb in its hair and a pair of white silk legs,
and presenting on the whole a feminine appearance. My gifted townsman stood gloomily apart,
with folded arms, and I could have wished that his curls and forehead had been more probable.
Several curious little circumstances transpired as the action proceeded. The late king of the
country not only appeared to have been troubled with a cough at the time of his decease, but to
have taken it with him to the tomb, and to have brought it back. The royal phantom also carried
a ghostly manuscript round its truncheon, to which it had the appearance of occasionally referring,
and that too, with an air of anxiety and a tendency to lose the place of reference which were
suggestive of a state of mortality. It was this, I conceive, which led to the Shade’s being advised
by the gallery to “turn over!”—a recommendation which it took extremely ill. It was likewise to
be noted of this majestic spirit, that whereas it always appeared with an air of having been
out a long time and walked an immense distance, it perceptibly came from a closely contiguous
wall. This occasioned its terrors to be received derisively. The Queen of Denmark, a very buxom
lady, though no doubt historically brazen, was considered by the public to have too much brass
about her; her chin being attached to her diadem by a broad band of that metal (as if she had a
gorgeous toothache), her waist being encircled by another, and each of her arms by another, so that
she was openly mentioned as “the kettle-drum.” The noble boy in the ancestral boots was inconsistent,
representing himself, as it were in one breath, as an able seaman, a strolling actor,
a grave-digger, a clergyman, and a person of the utmost importance at a Court fencing-match,
on the authority of whose practised eye and nice discrimination the finest strokes were judged.
This gradually led to a want of toleration for him, and even—on his being detected in
holy orders, and declining to perform the funeral service—to the general indignation taking the form
of nuts. Lastly, Ophelia was a prey to such slow musical madness, that when, in course of time,
she had taken off her white muslin scarf, folded it up, and buried it, a sulky man who had been
long cooling his impatient nose against an iron bar in the front row of the gallery, growled,
“Now the baby’s put to bed let’s have supper!” Which, to say the least of it, was out of keeping.
Upon my unfortunate townsman all these incidents accumulated with playful effect. Whenever that
undecided Prince had to ask a question or state a doubt, the public helped him out with it. As for
example; on the question whether ’twas nobler in the mind to suffer, some roared yes, and some no,
and some inclining to both opinions said “Toss up for it;” and quite a Debating Society arose.
When he asked what should such fellows as he do crawling between earth and heaven,
he was encouraged with loud cries of “Hear, hear!” When he appeared with his stocking
disordered (its disorder expressed, according to usage, by one very neat fold in the top,
which I suppose to be always got up with a flat iron), a conversation took place in the gallery
respecting the paleness of his leg, and whether it was occasioned by the turn the ghost had given
him. On his taking the recorders,—very like a little black flute that had just been played
in the orchestra and handed out at the door,—he was called upon unanimously for Rule Britannia.
When he recommended the player not to saw the air thus, the sulky man said, “And don’t you do it,
neither; you’re a deal worse than him!” And I grieve to add that peals of laughter greeted
Mr. Wopsle on every one of these occasions. But his greatest trials were in the churchyard,
which had the appearance of a primeval forest, with a kind of small ecclesiastical wash-house
on one side, and a turnpike gate on the other. Mr. Wopsle in a comprehensive black cloak,
being descried entering at the turnpike, the gravedigger was admonished in a friendly way,
“Look out! Here’s the undertaker a coming, to see how you’re a getting on with your work!” I believe
it is well known in a constitutional country that Mr. Wopsle could not possibly have returned the
skull, after moralizing over it, without dusting his fingers on a white napkin taken from his
breast; but even that innocent and indispensable action did not pass without the comment,
“Wai-ter!” The arrival of the body for interment (in an empty black box with the lid tumbling
open), was the signal for a general joy, which was much enhanced by the discovery, among the bearers,
of an individual obnoxious to identification. The joy attended Mr. Wopsle through his struggle
with Laertes on the brink of the orchestra and the grave, and slackened no more until
he had tumbled the king off the kitchen-table, and had died by inches from the ankles upward.
We had made some pale efforts in the beginning to applaud Mr. Wopsle; but they were too hopeless to
be persisted in. Therefore we had sat, feeling keenly for him, but laughing, nevertheless,
from ear to ear. I laughed in spite of myself all the time, the whole thing was so droll;
and yet I had a latent impression that there was something decidedly fine in Mr. Wopsle’s
elocution,—not for old associations’ sake, I am afraid, but because it was very slow, very dreary,
very uphill and downhill, and very unlike any way in which any man in any natural circumstances of
life or death ever expressed himself about anything. When the tragedy was over, and he
had been called for and hooted, I said to Herbert, “Let us go at once, or perhaps we shall meet him.”
We made all the haste we could downstairs, but we were not quick enough either. Standing at
the door was a Jewish man with an unnatural heavy smear of eyebrow,
who caught my eyes as we advanced, and said, when we came up with him,—
“Mr. Pip and friend?”
Identity of Mr. Pip and friend confessed.
“Mr. Waldengarver,” said the man, “would be glad to have the honour.”
“Waldengarver?” I repeated—when Herbert murmured in my ear, “Probably Wopsle.”
“Oh!” said I. “Yes. Shall we follow you?”
“A few steps, please.” When we were in a side
alley, he turned and asked, “How did you think he looked?—I dressed him.”
I don’t know what he had looked like, except a funeral; with the addition of a large Danish sun
or star hanging round his neck by a blue ribbon, that had given him the appearance
of being insured in some extraordinary Fire Office. But I said he had looked very nice.
“When he come to the grave,” said our conductor,
“he showed his cloak beautiful. But, judging from the wing, it looked to me that when he
see the ghost in the queen’s apartment, he might have made more of his stockings.”
I modestly assented, and we all fell through a little dirty swing door,
into a sort of hot packing-case immediately behind it. Here Mr. Wopsle was divesting
himself of his Danish garments, and here there was just room for us to look at him
over one another’s shoulders, by keeping the packing-case door, or lid, wide open.
“Gentlemen,” said Mr. Wopsle, “I am proud to see you. I hope, Mr. Pip,
you will excuse my sending round. I had the happiness to know you in former times,
and the Drama has ever had a claim which has ever been acknowledged, on the noble and the affluent.”
Meanwhile, Mr. Waldengarver, in a frightful perspiration,
was trying to get himself out of his princely sables.
“Skin the stockings off Mr. Waldengarver,” said the owner of that property,
“or you’ll bust ’em. Bust ’em, and you’ll bust five-and-thirty shillings. Shakspeare
never was complimented with a finer pair. Keep quiet in your chair now, and leave ’em to me.”
With that, he went upon his knees, and began to flay his victim; who,
on the first stocking coming off, would certainly have fallen over
backward with his chair, but for there being no room to fall anyhow.
I had been afraid until then to say a word about the play. But then,
Mr. Waldengarver looked up at us complacently, and said,—
“Gentlemen, how did it seem to you, to go, in front?”
Herbert said from behind (at the same time poking me), “Capitally.” So I said “Capitally.”
“How did you like my reading of the character,
gentlemen?” said Mr. Waldengarver, almost, if not quite, with patronage.
Herbert said from behind (again poking me), “Massive and concrete.” So I said boldly,
as if I had originated it, and must beg to insist upon it, “Massive and concrete.”
“I am glad to have your approbation, gentlemen,” said Mr. Waldengarver, with an air of dignity,
in spite of his being ground against the wall at the time, and holding on by the seat of the chair.
“But I’ll tell you one thing, Mr. Waldengarver,” said the man who was on his knees, “in which
you’re out in your reading. Now mind! I don’t care who says contrairy; I tell you so. You’re out in
your reading of Hamlet when you get your legs in profile. The last Hamlet as I dressed, made
the same mistakes in his reading at rehearsal, till I got him to put a large red wafer on each
of his shins, and then at that rehearsal (which was the last) I went in front, sir, to the back
of the pit, and whenever his reading brought him into profile, I called out “I don’t see no
wafers!” And at night his reading was lovely.” Mr. Waldengarver smiled at me, as much as to
say “a faithful Dependent—I overlook his folly;” and then said aloud, “My view is a
little classic and thoughtful for them here; but they will improve, they will improve.”
Herbert and I said together, O, no doubt they would improve.
“Did you observe, gentlemen,” said Mr. Waldengarver, “that there was a man in
the gallery who endeavoured to cast derision on the service,—I mean, the representation?”
We basely replied that we rather thought we had
noticed such a man. I added, “He was drunk, no doubt.”
“O dear no, sir,” said Mr. Wopsle, “not drunk.
His employer would see to that, sir. His employer would not allow him to be drunk.”
“You know his employer?” said I.
Mr. Wopsle shut his eyes, and opened them again; performing both ceremonies very
slowly. “You must have observed, gentlemen,” said he, “an ignorant and a blatant ass,
with a rasping throat and a countenance expressive of low malignity, who went
through—I will not say sustained—the rôle (if I may use a French expression) of Claudius,
King of Denmark. That is his employer, gentlemen. Such is the profession!”
Without distinctly knowing whether I should have been more sorry for Mr. Wopsle if he had been in
despair, I was so sorry for him as it was, that I took the opportunity of his turning
round to have his braces put on,—which jostled us out at the doorway,—to ask Herbert what he
thought of having him home to supper? Herbert said he thought it would be kind to do so;
therefore I invited him, and he went to Barnard’s with us, wrapped up to the eyes,
and we did our best for him, and he sat until two o’clock in the morning,
reviewing his success and developing his plans. I forget in detail what they were,
but I have a general recollection that he was to begin with reviving the Drama, and to end with
crushing it; inasmuch as his decease would leave it utterly bereft and without a chance or hope.
Miserably I went to bed after all, and miserably thought of Estella, and miserably dreamed that my
expectations were all cancelled, and that I had to give my hand in marriage to Herbert’s Clara,
or play Hamlet to Miss Havisham’s Ghost, before twenty thousand people, without knowing twenty
words of it. Chapter 32.